<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Gingras lab blog RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[The laboratory of Dr. Anne-Claude Gingras at the Lunenfeld in Toronto studies  mass spectrometry, interaction proteomics, cell signalling, CCM disease and COVID-19.]]></description><link>https://gingraslab.org</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:34:52 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Setting up a high-throughput antibody assay: it takes a village]]></title><description><![CDATA[In March 2020, about one week had passed since the WHO declared that COVID-19 is a pandemic (WHO Director-General's opening remarks at the…]]></description><link>https://gingraslab.org/blog/setting-up-a-high-throughput-antibody-assay-it-takes-a-village/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://gingraslab.org/blog/setting-up-a-high-throughput-antibody-assay-it-takes-a-village/</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Anne-Claude Gingras]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In March 2020, about one week had passed since the WHO declared that COVID-19 is a pandemic (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/director-general/speeches/detail/who-director-general-s-opening-remarks-at-the-media-briefing-on-covid-19---11-march-2020&quot;&gt;WHO Director-General&apos;s opening remarks at the media briefing on COVID-19 - 11 March 2020&lt;/a&gt;). Fatima Amanat and Florian Krammer had just posted their first preprint on a serological assay for COVID-19: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.03.17.20037713v1&quot;&gt;A serological assay to detect SARS-CoV-2 seroconversion in humans&lt;/a&gt;. In this manuscript, they described the production of proteins derived from SARS-CoV-2 and setting-up what is known in the field as an ELISA assay (acronym for Enzyme-Linked ImmunoSorbent Assay). In an ELISA, we attach a protein at the bottom of a well in a plastic plate and then add a sample, typically the serum component of blood, to the well to test for the presence of antibodies. These antibodies can recognize the protein, or “antigens,”  attached to the bottom of the well. We then remove the serum and add another antibody that can bind to any human antibody of a given type, such as the IgG antibody. This second antibody is also connected to an enzyme. Once you wash away the antibodies that have not been able to attach, you then provide the enzyme with a “substrate” upon which the enzyme will act to create a change in color or the emission of light, which you detect with a specific instrument. The Amanat and Krammer study succeeded in creating a manual colorimetric assay for the spike protein located on the surface of the SARS-CoV-2 virus and another one for the receptor binding domain of spike, that is responsible for binding to the protein ACE2 on the cells of the human host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 800px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/db573/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 40.5%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAICAYAAAD5nd/tAAAACXBIWXMAAAsTAAALEwEAmpwYAAACj0lEQVQozzXQW0jTcRwF8K+L5hapWEgD5xxUoMG8jSQyCtvF69JsOnWiom7qRN208jItsAVBmkQXHysiH3oQwV5KFAlsophzF3ez3P3i/nP+3UzXaL9Y0OOBz3k4B1gsFohbKuMQQmBXPUxQLY0WAgzGzQ9lZHziXT73sToP2upuEsqEHGA1FzP62Feo9ex8iHnn2ioJM+ivPmYyU2eKuOwNoZAIHA73RBGXTb2YVZj+eqSEsfahZuhOWUfyLL+S+bxskIJyEaBZBLUBgMThGnZqXxUdUAegnSAcGY2koGXnxmRBQfpccXHpsrA+HhSKMcLLyacnX2jWCFOi1oS3VbfpJQIhyMoFF0orBOfrBPwUAADuSCfhFo9HL+GVZ1bz+ZTp6fcEAAIBAE6xG5uSlLQ0KIjBXa8Djg8xQNEQ+G0GWH41/m8OABABgAwAZwAgVgRSPDktnnyaCgCpsZyZwyCl0KjU/2bmzTsAq8PD2D/Au4OHwdYAvi+1O9wZzl2c9us43BVFqGkPP+h3ejCGzROgeHxY757fJ8L8gXsm80+mWWM/67N5Ov1uXztmc/ca1MbrgGE+SSQcRNFICEXCIWSxWro0apXwOORFYdyHjnA3cjgs93RqXYXdZUQ47kWBgB3NryyOrc4tcczfv6GAy4m8Wyq0uPB5CjY0PxpM29bfNrvTa9q2Rje1ZsGycr3IZNQf7RhMLr1W+2dTa2z9sqC8ptfrDm0Ol0uv30Lrmi3Z7MzXbINKg1sMFo9Zo4usKNUKmBh/Qh4cktNGRh9Qh+Vy+rPJCWJtXUOSpFuWK5HJsts6e/Kbm5opjS0iolQ2wGgXi3N6pANZA/13k2M/SnvuXxK3iXIlHb15j+SKxL+U5EWCfMA5eAAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/6d911/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.webp 200w,
/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/60961/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.webp 400w,
/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/4b971/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.webp 800w,
/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/1aa16/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.webp 1200w,
/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/e3eeb/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.webp 1600w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/b4ec0/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.png 200w,
/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/24144/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.png 400w,
/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/29d74/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.png 800w,
/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/5c837/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.png 1200w,
/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/db573/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.png 1600w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/png&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/3914f0f1d985e5db03fdc7179175059b/29d74/ELISA_LTRI_just_cartoon.png&quot;
            alt=&quot;Description of the ELISA assay used at the LTRI for the detection of antibodies to SARS-CoV-2 proteins&quot;
            title=&quot;Description of the ELISA assay used at the LTRI for the detection of antibodies to SARS-CoV-2 proteins&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            decoding=&quot;async&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  Description of the ELISA assay used at the LTRI for the detection of antibodies to SARS-CoV-2 proteins. Created with BioRender.com.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This immediately caught my attention and I forwarded the preprint to my colleague Jeff Wrana with whom I co-direct the &lt;a href=&quot;nbcc.lunenfeld.ca&quot;&gt;Network Biology Collaborative Centre, NBCC&lt;/a&gt; at the Lunenfeld-Tanenbaum Research Institute (LTRI). This centre was developed thanks to funding from the Canadian Foundation for Innovation, Genome Canada and the government of Ontario, and it contains a suite of advanced instrumentation for systematically probing biological systems. One of the arms of the NBCC, led by Jeff, specializes in the automation of assays, including for protein-protein interactions. The binding of an antibody to an antigen (here a viral protein) is a relatively easy type of protein interaction to measure, since the binding affinity (how strongly the antibody binds to the target) is quite high. We felt that we were in a unique position to turn the manual assay reported by the Krammer group into an automated high-throughput assay that would enable us to test thousands of samples simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also believed that the high quality of the results reported in the Amanat/Krammer preprint should enable a clear diagnosis of individuals who have been previously infected with SARS-CoV-2. At the time, in Canada, testing for the presence of SARS-CoV-2 viral RNA (using a technique known as RT-PCR) was limited to people with a travelling history or of contact with travellers or confirmed cases. Any cases caught via community transmission, a huge driver of the pandemic, would have been missed. Within two days of the first email to Jeff Wrana, others had come together to help. Miriam Barrios-Rodiles, manager of the NBCC high-throughput screening facility, proposed a 384-well luminescence format for the assay, and connected with protein purification expert Yves Durocher at the National Research Council of Canada, NRC, who was setting up spike and RBD purification. Three days later, we also recruited on the “antigen team” from the University of Toronto, including James Rini, an expert in the structural biology of spike proteins, who was also in the process of purifying spike and RBD. Jeff also contacted Ken Hughes at Microbix, who provided protein from spike but also from the nucleocapsid protein. The nucleocapsid was not included in the Amanat/Krammer preprint, but this is a highly immunogenic protein, and many of the commercial assays are based upon its detection. We thought that including a nucleocapsid antigen as part of our screening strategy would increase the confidence in the identification of people with evidence of prior infection (and, as it turns out, this is now critically important to distinguish immunity originating from natural infection, which should induce a nucleocapsid response, from those of the vaccines). Eventually, we ended up using a nucleocapsid protein produced by Derek Ceccarelli in the Sicheri lab at LTRI, the RBD from James Rini and the spike trimer protein from Yves Durocher at the NRC.  As time went by, we also realized that a high-quality, sustainable and shareable (at least within the country) source of antigens was necessary, and this was made possible by a complete switch to antigens produced by the Durocher team at the NRC who also generated reagents for the detection of the antibodies, and also for calibration between assays (and eventually across laboratories). This collaboration with the NRC became the cornerstone of “made-in-Canada” serology testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having antigens (and the original protocols from Amanat/Krammer) was a necessary first step, but having access to samples to test them on was just as critical. Tara Moriarty and Karen Maxwell from the University of Toronto helped connect us to a team of immunologists at the University of Toronto, including Jen Gommerman and Mario Ostrowski. Mario in particular had taken large volume blood draws from some of the first patients with COVID-19 in Toronto, and Jen had banked pre-COVID era serum which she was able to share with us. In the days/weeks that followed, Allison McGeer and her colleagues at the Toronto Invasive Bacterial Disease Network (TIBDN) were able to provide additional samples from acute and convalescent patients, and she linked us with the Canadian Blood Services (CBS; Steve Drews) and the National Microbiology Laboratory of Canada (NML; Mike Drebot) who provided further samples for test development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With samples and antigens in hand, all we needed was a “dream team” of experimentalists to set-up and perform the assays, first in manual and then in automated fashion. We were already thinking about developing assays that not only measure the quantity of the antibodies produced, but also whether these antibodies are capable of preventing one of the most important steps in infection, spike protein binding to the receptor protein ACE2, which is on the surface of the host cells. The task of setting up and optimizing these assays was accomplished in record-time by a PhD student in my lab, Kento Abe, and my lab manager, research technician Bhavisha Rathod. They optimized all assay conditions to detect antibodies to each of the three antigens, and they developed different assays to look at different types of antibodies (IgG, IgA and IgM).  They tested dozens of conditions and several hundreds of samples manually until they were satisfied that the assay was working properly, and then worked with the robotics team to transfer the assay to the automated platform. Jenny Wang, automation specialist within the NBCC, and Miriam Barrios-Rodiles worked on transferring the manual assay to an automated assay that uses four times less material per assay and provides a more sensitive signal (Jenny is currently trying to further increase the throughput of the assay). They were able to demonstrate that the automated assay performed well and that if the same sample was analyzed twice with the same test, it returned the same results both times. Together, the team was then able to take a large number of samples that had been collected prior to the COVID-19 pandemic (presumed negatives, about 300), and confirmed COVID-19 samples (provided by the CBS, Mario Ostrowski or Allison McGeer and the TIBDN team; also about 300), so that we could define what was the sensitivity and the specificity of each individual assay. In other words, how many of the pre-COVID serum samples would be (falsely) called positive by each individual assays (false positive rate, a measure of specificity) and how many samples from convalescent individuals with confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection would be correctly identified as positive (sensitivity). We also realized early on that requiring a sample to score “positive” on two or more of the three assays really helped us reduce the false positive rate, while maintaining the sensitivity at an acceptable rate. This strategy is particularly important if the expected seroprevalence is low as it was in Canada in the first waves of infection, and prior to the introduction of vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 800px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/43ad0/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 71.50000000000001%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDAAoHBwgHBgoICAgLCgoLDhgQDg0NDh0VFhEYIx8lJCIfIiEmKzcvJik0KSEiMEExNDk7Pj4+JS5ESUM8SDc9Pjv/2wBDAQoLCw4NDhwQEBw7KCIoOzs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozs7Ozv/wgARCAAOABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAUBAwT/xAAUAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAB/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAFoUp0g3Af/xAAbEAEBAAIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAABAgMEABITIv/aAAgBAQABBQLN9TUngDzbtw4+6ppVZ//EABcRAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABERL/2gAIAQMBAT8Bbho//8QAGBEAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECERL/2gAIAQIBAT8BUbMn/8QAHRAAAgEEAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAAiEyQRNRgf/aAAgBAQAGPwKstXVpxZEDI7nUY2ZQiYxUvZ//xAAcEAACAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQBRITGBsdH/2gAIAQEAAT8hQABBGh5MakUpxSQN9oMtd8fg7DUwD6fyf//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQ8+//xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQD/2gAIAQMBAT8QirhpZv/EABcRAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEUH/2gAIAQIBAT8QQIxn/8QAHBAAAwEAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhADFBUYHB/9oACAEBAAE/EHUEqYhfZJhi4HKPSwu4r5x4xIFJ/GquTSslczhDOsF0isdJCwkecIDh/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/6d911/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.webp 200w,
/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/60961/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.webp 400w,
/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/4b971/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.webp 800w,
/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/1aa16/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.webp 1200w,
/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/e3eeb/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.webp 1600w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/7a70a/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.jpg 200w,
/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/b2cea/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.jpg 400w,
/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/93d59/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.jpg 800w,
/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/0516a/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.jpg 1200w,
/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/43ad0/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.jpg 1600w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/4b5a316b00d883d8e577d3434456cae3/93d59/Covid_researchers_MSH-6.jpg&quot;
            alt=&quot;PhD student Kento Abe and research technician Bhavisha Rathod, seen optimizing the manual ELISA assay&quot;
            title=&quot;PhD student Kento Abe and research technician Bhavisha Rathod, seen optimizing the manual ELISA assay&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            decoding=&quot;async&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  PhD student Kento Abe and research technician Bhavisha Rathod, seen optimizing the manual ELISA assay. Picture courtesy of Sinai Health.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first large-scale application of the automated assays included measurements of IgG, IgA and IgM to the three antigens spike, RBD and the nucleocapsid. We performed these measurements on nearly 500 serum samples from patients with an acute COVID-19 infection (all collected through the TIBDN in Toronto) to look at the dynamics of antibody production in the three to four months following an infection. The profiling by the Gommerman team of antibodies in the saliva enabled us to compare serum and saliva antibody levels for many of the same patients, and to conclude that saliva is an appropriate alternative body fluid for antibody measurements. We also were able to report, in agreement with several other reports published around the same time and since then, that IgG but not IgA or IgM are still detectable many months after the infection. The study was published online in October 2020 (with students Baweleta Isho, Kento Abe, Michelle Zuo and Alainna Jamal sharing co-first authorship; &lt;a href=&quot;https://immunology.sciencemag.org/content/5/52/eabe5511&quot;&gt;Persistence of serum and saliva antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2 spike antigens in COVID-19 patients&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our success in setting up these assays on an automated platform rapidly drew the attention of other groups that were interested in looking at antibodies to SARS-CoV-2 proteins for either immune correlates or seroprevalence studies (most of the studies that are still ongoing have now pivoted to vaccine response studies). This would involve more than 25 projects, with 80,000 samples processed so far (the majority with three assays per sample). Each of the projects comes with unique challenges, including different labeling schemes, sample types (liquid blood, dried blood spots), requirement for measurements of different antibodies, timelines for reporting to participants, etc. The logistics associated with these projects therefore require a high level of organization and tracking, both on the administrative side and on the ground, and the development of quality control steps and automated data analysis and visualization tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this process, NBCC manager Karen Colwill played a critical support role. She made sure that we had material transfer agreements and research ethics board approvals in place, worked on our biosafety protocols, and coordinated with Bhavisha Rathod and Miriam Barrios-Rodiles to order materia, which, as it turns out, was not an easy task in pandemic times, with delays and shortages affecting the availability of plasticware that is necessary for the assays. As we moved into production mode with the high-throughput ELISA assays, Karen took on an increasingly important role, including tracking projects and scheduling samples to be run, and manually reviewing the data generated in each batch and reporting the results to the project leads. On the ground, Bhavisha Rathod held down the fort and worked with a team of recently-recruited individuals (Mahya Fazel-Zarandi, Mariam Iskilova, Queenie Hu, Monica Dayam) to receive all the samples, make sure that any potential virus was inactivated, prepare them for analysis in automated runs, and store the remaining samples properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 800px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/db573/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 37.5%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAICAIAAAB2/0i6AAAACXBIWXMAAAsTAAALEwEAmpwYAAAB40lEQVQY0wXBy2sTQRwA4P2jKuIhYtX2UqsGqUWCaA82l/pA0CKinnKQgvUgQYViVJCWqi0iGqvG2EOawCa2CXlUm8zOzsy+stk02Uc2m939+X2cZZqKLJv9PoQAAN7QUxW1o+v+yAeAkefpbZ1RZpkmAPz8mpmNTlyNRaNnTsVmz3OohQiRWkgwe30AYEwSMUMIq4oKIXQ6BsaEYIIFIQyg8Du3/vLB5yd3nz+8VctvcoyochMpxZKBsOv7KP2NpLfo/l9ZwEN3qMma+K9F9ypiueLabi6/fWd+ZjkeS8zPrSSXOJTbo+8/yL+yBqWWN9p5lZJSr5VMRi2WLNOUicb4XaVYotXawB409gsLN65dn7vy4vHNd8nbXHE9Tao1Kqsd3bBtO/cli0pVqYmYyBxnINYF4e2qtLomftwY9Cy+zE9NjccvL8QvXUwk7nPbmbquHypU6erdIPAz36uNmqIwXWZaCFAuNLPJlYPNTwepN+6h+We39PTZ0uK9xcjRI2PjJ7m2pgkYM00b+QEA2JZDKRUlyXFdAHBdT2SSQIhmdAGA5/mNH1try49mTkciJ6Y5zxk4THIqlaDXAwDfGzlt3ao3hoIAAGEQ2ka3T4gtYgDI53cunJuITx0/e2xscnL6P1x4fenGmyJEAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/6d911/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.webp 200w,
/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/60961/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.webp 400w,
/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/4b971/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.webp 800w,
/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/1aa16/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.webp 1200w,
/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/e3eeb/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.webp 1600w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/b4ec0/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.png 200w,
/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/24144/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.png 400w,
/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/29d74/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.png 800w,
/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/5c837/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.png 1200w,
/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/db573/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.png 1600w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/png&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/a6dea9c48c3a77d29cd11609688b856e/29d74/Karen_Bhavisha_CanPath.png&quot;
            alt=&quot;Karen Colwill (centre right) reviewing the results for a seroprevalence and vaccination study at a team meeting&quot;
            title=&quot;Karen Colwill (centre right) reviewing the results for a seroprevalence and vaccination study at a team meeting&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            decoding=&quot;async&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  Karen Colwill (centre right) reviewing the results for a seroprevalence and vaccination study at a team meeting. Also pictured: Bhavisha Rathod (bottom) and Anne-Claude Gingras (top). The visualization show has been developed by Adrian Pasculescu.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While our assay relies on automation, the initial sample intake is very much manual and varies for each project. For example, in a recent serology surveillance study run by Statistics Canada using dried blood spot cards, samples came individually packed in a small envelope, with 10 envelopes placed into a small plastic bag and these bags packaged inside a large container. Each outside bag, then inside envelope, needed to be opened, the barcode on the dried blood spot card read, and a small portion of the dried blood spot cut out with a laser puncher into a plate containing 96 separate wells. Then the card needed to be put back into its place and stored safely. The antibodies contained on the dried blood spot needed to be extracted by the addition of a liquid containing detergent before they could be brought to the robot for the assays. In some other projects, liquid blood product (most often serum) is provided, most of the time frozen, and hand-written or typed labels instead of barcodes are often affixed to the samples. These sample identifiers must be manually transferred to our database and verified so errors are not made. The serum is transferred to a well of a 96-well plate that contains detergent to inactivate any potential virus in a specific order before being brought to the robot. The automated runs are set-up by Jenny Wang (and more recently Mariam Iskilova and Mahya Fazel-Zarandi), and the results are transferred by the operator to our server.  Biostatistician Adrian Pasculescu created automated scripts to perform quality control checks and extract the data for all the test samples in a given batch. We always express the values detected in an assay against those detected with a calibration standard since this makes it easier to compare the studies from day to day. Both Adrian and Kento Abe developed other visualization and analysis tools that make it easier to see what are the levels of antibodies in a specific sample or across multiple samples within a project.  This also facilitates communication with our external partners, and the preparation of data for publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each person has a critically important role to play in the development of these assays or their implementation across projects. Teamwork and communication are critically important, as is the leadership of team leads. We also have developed complementary assays that are not currently amenable to automation, but provide critical information on the ability of antibodies to block the entry of a virus into cells (these assays were developed by PhD student Reuben Samson with former postdoctoral fellow Payman Samavarchi-Tehrani and are now performed by Queenie Hu and Reuben). Importantly, we have worked closely with different investigators across the country to profile antibody levels across multiple cohorts. These interactions have been rewarding to the team, especially as our work may have helped inform some public health decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this endeavour, we have been fortunate to secure funding that has allowed us to set-up the assays, notably through the Sinai Health Foundation that secured donations from the RBC Foundation, the Krembil Foundation and QuestCap early in the pandemic. Our collaborations/services to different research projects have led to additional funding primarily through the CIHR, the Ontario government and more recently the COVID-19 Immunity Task Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this piece, I only focused on the contributions of our team at the LTRI and NBCC and our close collaborators in setting-up the automated ELISA assays. Future blog spots will highlight some of the important projects we are assisting using these assays.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Illuminating the organization of the human cell]]></title><description><![CDATA[Researchers from Sinai Health have published a study providing an ultra-detailed look at the organization of a living human cell, providing…]]></description><link>https://gingraslab.org/blog/illuminating-the-organization-of-the-human-cell/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://gingraslab.org/blog/illuminating-the-organization-of-the-human-cell/</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Francesco Zangari]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Researchers from Sinai Health have published a study providing an ultra-detailed look at the organization of a living human cell, providing a new tool that can help scientists around the world better understand what happens during disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-021-03592-2&quot;&gt;new study&lt;/a&gt;, out today in the journal Nature, was conducted in the laboratory of Dr. Anne-Claude Gingras, a senior investigator at the LTRI and professor in the Department of Molecular Genetics at the University of Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The human body is composed of trillions of cells that are each further separated into different compartments with dedicated functions, much like a house has different rooms for sleeping or preparing food. These compartments, which are called organelles, each contain different proteins that perform specific activities associated with the compartment. Prominent examples of organelles include the mitochondria, responsible for generating the cell&apos;s primary energy supply, and the endoplasmic reticulum, a key structure for protein production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing which proteins are residing in which organelles is an important first step towards understanding the role of each cellular protein. However, approaches taken previously have most often relied on methods that first kill the cells before trying to separate the organelles from one another (akin to taking the house apart and trying to isolate each of the individual rooms). These approaches tend to provide only crude views of the organization of a cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new study, called the “Human Cell Map”, was undertaken by co-first authors Christopher D. Go and Dr. James D. R. Knight, who surveyed the human cell landscape using 192 markers for proteins known to reside in specific organelles that can “tag” neighbouring proteins in the same compartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Human Cell Map was able to predict the localization of 4000 proteins across all compartments in living human cells,” explains Go. “We sampled all the major organelles of the human cell and used innovative analysis to create the highest resolution map to date, with high accuracy in predicting novel localizations for many unmapped proteins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gingras lab develops tools to detect proteins using instruments known as mass spectrometers. In the new study, they have purified the proteins that are “tagged” by organelle markers and identified each of them by mass spectrometry. Computational tools were next used to reconstruct the organization of a human cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Through our research, we have shown that we can precisely localize thousands of proteins at a time with relatively little effort,” said Dr. Knight, a bioinformatician in the Gingras Lab at the LTRI. “Previous methods for localizing a protein required each protein to be investigated individually or required a limited focus.” Given the expansive nature of the Human Cell Map, the team also created an &lt;a href=&quot;https://humancellmap.org&quot;&gt;analysis portal&lt;/a&gt; to allow researchers around the world to delve deeper into the data. Users can scan each of the 192 markers in detail and compare their own data on protein localization to predictions made in the Human Cell Map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knight said while this work provides a greater understanding of the organization within the human cell, it also can be leveraged to better understand what happens during disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Human diseases are typically characterized at the molecular level by proteins with aberrant behaviour that cause the cell to behave in pathological ways. In these situations, proteins will often change where they reside in the cell,” said Dr. Knight. “Our research is a first step in addressing this challenge in normal cells and we can use it for comparisons against altered cell states, such as disease conditions, to identify proteins with unexpected localizations that may help us understand a diseased cell better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team said the map will now be used in a variety of projects to help shed additional light on protein localization in human cells. Future efforts will include using chemical, viral and disease conditions to better characterize how cells adapt structurally to these stressors. This can inform future research efforts towards a mechanistic understanding of diseased states and the development of future therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was made possible by a Canadian Institutes of Health Research grant, as well as funding to the Network Biology Collaborative Centre at the LTRI, a facility supported by the Canada Foundation for Innovation, the Ontario Government, Genome Canada and Ontario Genomics. Funding for the analysis portal was provided by Compute Canada. Funding of Go’s stipend was partially provided through a CIHR Banting studentship.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Sinai Health study illuminates nutrient acquisition pathway used by cancer cells]]></title><description><![CDATA[Scientists at Sinai Health’s Lunenfeld-Tanenbaum Research Institute (LTRI) and the University of Toronto have identified a new mechanism…]]></description><link>https://gingraslab.org/blog/new-sinai-health-study-illuminates-nutrient-acquisition-pathway-used-by-cancer-cells/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://gingraslab.org/blog/new-sinai-health-study-illuminates-nutrient-acquisition-pathway-used-by-cancer-cells/</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Francesco Zangari]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Scientists at Sinai Health’s Lunenfeld-Tanenbaum Research Institute (LTRI) and the University of Toronto have identified a new mechanism used by cells during the acquisition of key nutrients, revealing potential vulnerabilities in cancer cells that may lead to the development of targeted therapeutics. The findings were published in the journal &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/370/6514/351&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; on October 15th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sustain life, human cells require a stable supply of nutrients. Amino acids, the building blocks needed for making proteins, are among the most critical. With proteins making up over half the “dry” mass of cells, they must constantly work to maintain sufficient amino acid levels to enable proper growth and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While cells normally import amino acids directly from their surrounding milieu, another way they may acquire amino acids in certain situations is through a form of “cellular drinking”, a process termed macropinocytosis. In macropinocytosis, cells take up proteins from their surrounding environment and break them down within the lysosome, a digestive compartment in the cell. How exactly amino acids salvaged from proteins inside lysosomes stimulates cell growth has remained a mystery in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study was conducted in the laboratory of Dr. Anne-Claude Gingras, a senior scientist at the LTRI and professor in the Department of Molecular Genetics at the University of Toronto. First author Dr. Geoffrey G. Hesketh, a postdoctoral fellow in the Gingras laboratory, focused on the major cellular amino acid sensor known as mechanistic target of rapamycin complex 1 (mTORC1). mTORC1 controls the cellular machineries that make more proteins, and does so only when sufficient nutrients, including amino acids, are present. “We already knew how mTORC1 becomes activated by free amino acids, and this involves several proteins that work in concert,” said Hesketh, “but whether the same proteins also help activate mTORC1 when the macropinocytosis-lysosome pathway is used instead was not known”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gingras lab develops approaches to detect the localization of proteins within different cellular compartments using instruments known as mass spectrometers. Dr. Hesketh applied these approaches to provide a molecular snapshot of all the proteins that reside on the surface of lysosomes inside living cells. This revealed an unsuspected connection between the mTORC1 components and a protein complex already known to be important for  lysosome function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By coupling these experiments with CRISPR gene editing, researchers were able to tease out the alternative mechanism of mTORC1 activation by lysosome-derived amino acids compared to those that are acquired in free form by the cell. “We discovered that free amino acids signal via a different pathway than those coming from inside the lysosome within the cell,” says Dr. Jim Dennis, a study co-author and senior investigator at the LTRI. “Importantly, we have revealed how this new regulatory circuit works as a switch between free and salvaged amino acids in the regulation of mTORC1”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these results provided researchers with a better understanding of how nutrients control cell growth, this study also has critical implications for identifying potential cancer vulnerabilities, as certain forms of cancer (such as pancreatic cancer) rely on macropinocytosis to sustain their rapid growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The ability to use whole proteins as a source of amino acids is thought to allow pancreatic cancer cells to grow and survive deep inside tumours that don’t receive a normal supply of nutrients from the blood,” says Hesketh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we can understand the molecular detail of how this alternative nutrient acquisition pathway works inside cancer cells, then we might be able to identify new drugs that could target this pathway – effectively shutting down their food supply and starving the cancer cells to death”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future avenues of research will be aimed at developing a more complete understanding of how this alternative mTORC1 activation pathway actually supports cancer cell survival. This may reveal to researchers which parts of this pathway may be good targets for cancer therapeutic development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was made possible by operating funds from the Canadian Cancer Society Research Institute and a Canadian Institutes of Health Research Foundation Grant, as well as funding to the LTRI Network Biology Collaborative Centre through Genome Canada, Ontario Genomics and Canada Foundation for Innovation. Funding of Dr. Hesketh’s salary was partially provided through Parkinson Canada and a gift from the Glowinsky-Sandler family.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>