<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Gingras lab blog RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[The laboratory of Dr. Anne-Claude Gingras at the Lunenfeld in Toronto studies  mass spectrometry, interaction proteomics, cell signalling, CCM disease and COVID-19.]]></description><link>https://gingraslab.org</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 15:55:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Illuminating the organization of the human cell]]></title><description><![CDATA[Researchers from Sinai Health have published a study providing an ultra-detailed look at the organization of a living human cell, providing…]]></description><link>https://gingraslab.org/blog/illuminating-the-organization-of-the-human-cell/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://gingraslab.org/blog/illuminating-the-organization-of-the-human-cell/</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Francesco Zangari]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Researchers from Sinai Health have published a study providing an ultra-detailed look at the organization of a living human cell, providing a new tool that can help scientists around the world better understand what happens during disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-021-03592-2&quot;&gt;new study&lt;/a&gt;, out today in the journal Nature, was conducted in the laboratory of Dr. Anne-Claude Gingras, a senior investigator at the LTRI and professor in the Department of Molecular Genetics at the University of Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The human body is composed of trillions of cells that are each further separated into different compartments with dedicated functions, much like a house has different rooms for sleeping or preparing food. These compartments, which are called organelles, each contain different proteins that perform specific activities associated with the compartment. Prominent examples of organelles include the mitochondria, responsible for generating the cell&apos;s primary energy supply, and the endoplasmic reticulum, a key structure for protein production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing which proteins are residing in which organelles is an important first step towards understanding the role of each cellular protein. However, approaches taken previously have most often relied on methods that first kill the cells before trying to separate the organelles from one another (akin to taking the house apart and trying to isolate each of the individual rooms). These approaches tend to provide only crude views of the organization of a cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new study, called the “Human Cell Map”, was undertaken by co-first authors Christopher D. Go and Dr. James D. R. Knight, who surveyed the human cell landscape using 192 markers for proteins known to reside in specific organelles that can “tag” neighbouring proteins in the same compartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Human Cell Map was able to predict the localization of 4000 proteins across all compartments in living human cells,” explains Go. “We sampled all the major organelles of the human cell and used innovative analysis to create the highest resolution map to date, with high accuracy in predicting novel localizations for many unmapped proteins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gingras lab develops tools to detect proteins using instruments known as mass spectrometers. In the new study, they have purified the proteins that are “tagged” by organelle markers and identified each of them by mass spectrometry. Computational tools were next used to reconstruct the organization of a human cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Through our research, we have shown that we can precisely localize thousands of proteins at a time with relatively little effort,” said Dr. Knight, a bioinformatician in the Gingras Lab at the LTRI. “Previous methods for localizing a protein required each protein to be investigated individually or required a limited focus.” Given the expansive nature of the Human Cell Map, the team also created an &lt;a href=&quot;https://humancellmap.org&quot;&gt;analysis portal&lt;/a&gt; to allow researchers around the world to delve deeper into the data. Users can scan each of the 192 markers in detail and compare their own data on protein localization to predictions made in the Human Cell Map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knight said while this work provides a greater understanding of the organization within the human cell, it also can be leveraged to better understand what happens during disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Human diseases are typically characterized at the molecular level by proteins with aberrant behaviour that cause the cell to behave in pathological ways. In these situations, proteins will often change where they reside in the cell,” said Dr. Knight. “Our research is a first step in addressing this challenge in normal cells and we can use it for comparisons against altered cell states, such as disease conditions, to identify proteins with unexpected localizations that may help us understand a diseased cell better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team said the map will now be used in a variety of projects to help shed additional light on protein localization in human cells. Future efforts will include using chemical, viral and disease conditions to better characterize how cells adapt structurally to these stressors. This can inform future research efforts towards a mechanistic understanding of diseased states and the development of future therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was made possible by a Canadian Institutes of Health Research grant, as well as funding to the Network Biology Collaborative Centre at the LTRI, a facility supported by the Canada Foundation for Innovation, the Ontario Government, Genome Canada and Ontario Genomics. Funding for the analysis portal was provided by Compute Canada. Funding of Go’s stipend was partially provided through a CIHR Banting studentship.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Sinai Health study illuminates nutrient acquisition pathway used by cancer cells]]></title><description><![CDATA[Scientists at Sinai Health’s Lunenfeld-Tanenbaum Research Institute (LTRI) and the University of Toronto have identified a new mechanism…]]></description><link>https://gingraslab.org/blog/new-sinai-health-study-illuminates-nutrient-acquisition-pathway-used-by-cancer-cells/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://gingraslab.org/blog/new-sinai-health-study-illuminates-nutrient-acquisition-pathway-used-by-cancer-cells/</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Francesco Zangari]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Scientists at Sinai Health’s Lunenfeld-Tanenbaum Research Institute (LTRI) and the University of Toronto have identified a new mechanism used by cells during the acquisition of key nutrients, revealing potential vulnerabilities in cancer cells that may lead to the development of targeted therapeutics. The findings were published in the journal &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/370/6514/351&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; on October 15th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sustain life, human cells require a stable supply of nutrients. Amino acids, the building blocks needed for making proteins, are among the most critical. With proteins making up over half the “dry” mass of cells, they must constantly work to maintain sufficient amino acid levels to enable proper growth and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While cells normally import amino acids directly from their surrounding milieu, another way they may acquire amino acids in certain situations is through a form of “cellular drinking”, a process termed macropinocytosis. In macropinocytosis, cells take up proteins from their surrounding environment and break them down within the lysosome, a digestive compartment in the cell. How exactly amino acids salvaged from proteins inside lysosomes stimulates cell growth has remained a mystery in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study was conducted in the laboratory of Dr. Anne-Claude Gingras, a senior scientist at the LTRI and professor in the Department of Molecular Genetics at the University of Toronto. First author Dr. Geoffrey G. Hesketh, a postdoctoral fellow in the Gingras laboratory, focused on the major cellular amino acid sensor known as mechanistic target of rapamycin complex 1 (mTORC1). mTORC1 controls the cellular machineries that make more proteins, and does so only when sufficient nutrients, including amino acids, are present. “We already knew how mTORC1 becomes activated by free amino acids, and this involves several proteins that work in concert,” said Hesketh, “but whether the same proteins also help activate mTORC1 when the macropinocytosis-lysosome pathway is used instead was not known”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gingras lab develops approaches to detect the localization of proteins within different cellular compartments using instruments known as mass spectrometers. Dr. Hesketh applied these approaches to provide a molecular snapshot of all the proteins that reside on the surface of lysosomes inside living cells. This revealed an unsuspected connection between the mTORC1 components and a protein complex already known to be important for  lysosome function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By coupling these experiments with CRISPR gene editing, researchers were able to tease out the alternative mechanism of mTORC1 activation by lysosome-derived amino acids compared to those that are acquired in free form by the cell. “We discovered that free amino acids signal via a different pathway than those coming from inside the lysosome within the cell,” says Dr. Jim Dennis, a study co-author and senior investigator at the LTRI. “Importantly, we have revealed how this new regulatory circuit works as a switch between free and salvaged amino acids in the regulation of mTORC1”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these results provided researchers with a better understanding of how nutrients control cell growth, this study also has critical implications for identifying potential cancer vulnerabilities, as certain forms of cancer (such as pancreatic cancer) rely on macropinocytosis to sustain their rapid growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The ability to use whole proteins as a source of amino acids is thought to allow pancreatic cancer cells to grow and survive deep inside tumours that don’t receive a normal supply of nutrients from the blood,” says Hesketh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we can understand the molecular detail of how this alternative nutrient acquisition pathway works inside cancer cells, then we might be able to identify new drugs that could target this pathway – effectively shutting down their food supply and starving the cancer cells to death”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future avenues of research will be aimed at developing a more complete understanding of how this alternative mTORC1 activation pathway actually supports cancer cell survival. This may reveal to researchers which parts of this pathway may be good targets for cancer therapeutic development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was made possible by operating funds from the Canadian Cancer Society Research Institute and a Canadian Institutes of Health Research Foundation Grant, as well as funding to the LTRI Network Biology Collaborative Centre through Genome Canada, Ontario Genomics and Canada Foundation for Innovation. Funding of Dr. Hesketh’s salary was partially provided through Parkinson Canada and a gift from the Glowinsky-Sandler family.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>